Finding aid to the Ely Chinoy papers CA.MS.00386
Smith College Archives
Ely Chinoy papers
1921-1977
1953 - 1977
Smith College Archives
Chinoy, Ely, 1921 - 1975.
CA.MS.00386
1.042 linear feet (3 containers)
Faculty. Department of Sociology. Contains various documents relating to the career of Ely Chinoy at Smith College including correspondence, photographs, news clippings, published works, research, course materials, and programs.
Biographical / Historical
Ely Chinoy was born on September 5, 1921 in Newark, New Jersey to Sam and Bella Chinoy. He received his B.A. from the University of Newark (now Rutgers University) in 1942 summa cum laude. In the years following he held teaching positions at the Newark College of Engineering, Washington Square College of New York University and at the University of Toronto where he held the 1946 - 1947 Social Science Research Council Fellowship. In 1951 he became an instructor of Sociology at Smith College. Two years later he received his Ph.D. from Columbia University.
Chinoy's first book, Automobile Workers and the American Dream, was published in 1955 and became a landmark study of the factory and, in particular, the description and analysis of behavioral psychology of assembly line workers. Other books produced by Chinoy include Sociological Perspective (1954), Society (1961) and The Urban Future (1973). His texts have been translated into various languages including Portuguese, Spanish, Italian, Serbo-Croatian and Japanese.
Professionally, Chinoy was incredibly active. From 1959 to 1960 he served as an assistant editor of the American Sociological Review, becoming an associate editor from 1961 until 1964. In 1963 he travelled to England and served as a Fulbright professor at the University of Leicester in addition to lecturing at Oxford, the London School of Economics and at several research instituted associated with former Yugoslavic universities. He was a member of the American Sociological Association, the Eastern Sociological Association, the American Association of University Professors and the American Civil Liberties Union. In 1971 he resumed his Fulbright activities and travelled to the Philippines to lecture. Internally, Chinoy played an important role on several committees, including serving as the President of the Smith College chapter of the American Association of University Professors and the special committee on co-education in 1970 - 1971, which recommended that Smith College remain a women's college.
On April 21, 1975 Chinoy was killed returning home from a speaking engagement in Boston, Massachusetts. His car veered off the road, struck the guardrail and overturned several times. He was 53 years old.
Chinoy's wife, Helen Krich Chinoy (1922 - 2010) was an instructor of Theatre and Speech at Smith College from 1952 until 1986. His son Michael was CNN's Beijing Bureau Chief from 1987 to 1995 during which time he covered the 1989 events at Tiananmen Square. In 1995 he taught as a visiting professor at Smith College. Chinoy's daughter Claire attended Radcliffe and later married David Jones, a flamenco artist known popularly as 'Gypsy Dave'.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains materials from Chinoy's work in the Sociology and Anthropology departments at Smith College and includes course material, departmental correspondence and photographs. There are also a number of obituaries. The bulk of the collection is comprised of Chinoy's published works in English and in translation as well as .75 linear feet of research for "Coeducation at Smith College: A Report to the President and the College Planning Committee".
Arrangement
This collection is organized into four series:
Biographical
Professional
Publications
Research
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source unknown.
Related Materials
The following materials are available via the Five College Digital Access Project:
Faculty Planning Committee Records - Coeducation Materials, 1967 - 1971
The following materials are available in the Smith College Archives:
Helen Krich Chinoy Papers, 1922 - 2010
Smith College. Department of Anthropology
Smith College. Department of Sociology
The following related materials are available at the Walter P. Reuther Library at Wayne State University:
Ely Chinoy Papers (bulk 1936 - 1983)
Coeducation -- Massachusetts -- Northampton; correspondence; manuscripts for publishing; research (document genres); Chinoy, Ely.; Smith College -- Administration; Smith College - Anthropology; Smith College. College Planning Committee.; Smith College - Faculty - History - Sources; Smith College -- Sociology
- Series I: Biographical
  - clippings regarding automobile accident, 1975 - 1977 (Box 705, Folder 1)
  - "Humanizing Work: A Symposium in Honor of Ely Chinoy", 1977 (Box 705, Folder 2)
- Series II: Professional
  - correspondence, 1964 - 1965 (Box 705, Folder 3)
  - faculty file, 1963 - 1975 (Box 705, Folder 4)
- Series III: Publications
  - Coeducation, Anyone?, 1971 (Box 705, Folder 5)
  - Knowledge and Action: The Role of Sociology, 1970 (Box 705, Folder 6)
  - releases and reviews, 1952; 1955 (Box 705, Folder 7)
  - Society: An introduction to Sociology, 2nd Edition, 1967 (Box 705)
  - Sociological Perspective, 2nd Edition, 1968 (Box 705)
  - Automobile Workers and the American Dream, 1965 (Box 705)
  - Perspectiva Sociologica, 1967 (Box 705)
  - Sociological Perspective: Basic Concepts and Their Application, 1963 (Box 705)
  - Introduccion a la Sociologia, undated (Box 705)
  - Sociedade: Uma Introduccian Sociologia, 1967 (Box 705)
  - La Sociedad: Una Introduccian Sociologia, 1967 (Box 705)
  - Sociological Perspective (Japanese translation), 1968 (Box 705)
- Series IV: Research
  - Co-education at Smith, 1969 (Box 706, Folder 1)
  - Conference on the Undergraduate Education of Women, July 1969, 1968 - 1969 (Box 706, Folder 2)
  - Faculty Views- Coeducation, May 1968 (Box 706, Folder 3)
  - Secondary School Questionnaire (Box 706, Folder 4)
  - Smith College and the Issue of Co-education, 1968 (Box 706, Folder 5)
  - Student Survey on Co-education, 1968 - 1970 (Box 706, Folder 6)
  - Faculty Planning Committee Reports, 1967 - 1971 (Box 706, Folder 7)
  - Co-education at other Institutions- Bennington College, 1968 (Box 706, Folder 8)
  - Co-education at other Institutions- Lafayette College, 1969 (Box 706, Folder 9)
  - Co-education at other Institutions- Princeton University, 1967 - 1969 (Box 706, Folder 10)
  - Co-education at other Institutions- Vassar College, 1967 (Box 706, Folder 11)
  - Co-education at other Institutions- Wabash College, 1971 (Box 706, Folder 12)
  - Co-education Computer Data- Secondary School, 1970 (Box 706.1, Folder 1)
  - Co-education Computer Data- Secondary School, 1970 (Box 706.1, Folder 2)
  - Co-education Computer Data- Secondary School, 1970 (Box 706.1, Folder 3)
  - Co-education Computer Data- Secondary School, 1970 (Box 706.1, Folder 4)